Darío Ríos Navarro

Machine Learning Engineer | Full Stack Developer | Project Management | Web Accessibility **Expert**

Costa Rica Desamparados, Alajuela +506 88132815

dario.rios@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/darioriosnavarro/

SUMMARY

Machine Leaning Engineer focus in MLOps. Senior Full Stack Developer. Project Manager profile. Web Accessibility expert. Java Developer for fifteen years. Experienced with all stages of the development cycle for web projects and agile web development. Well-versed in numerous programming languages including Java, React, Python, PySpark, HTML5, PHP, JavaScript, CSS, MySQL, SQL Server, Oracle, etc. Strong background in project management, customer relations.

EXPERIENCE

Machine Learning Engineer (Stack Software engineer) 03/2023 - ACQUIRED KNOWLEDGE present

Western Union, Santa Ana, San José.

- Developing and deployment of models in UAT and production in AWS ECS Fargate services. Helping the decision scientist team with support of models created for risk management for India and Costa Rica.
- Helping the decision scientist team with support of models created for risk management for India and Costa Rica in a average of 5 models for month
- Migration of On prem servers to AWS in 100% for all the risk models on production
- Leading the migration of models to Dataiku with 95% of effectiveness

Technologies applied: Java, Python, PySpark, R, Cloudbees, Spinnaker, OpenSearch, Dynatrace, AWS Fargate, ECR, Dataiku

Senior Full Stack Developer 12/2020 - 03/2023 Edify Software Consulting, Alaiuela.

- Developing for front-end and back-end to clients in the United States, especially in systems related to educational and university technologies.
- Leading a project of highest value for the company and implementing new enhancement with 95% of successful

Technologies applied: React JS, Java, Spring, Spring security, Spring boot, Gradle, Hibernate, Spring JPA, PostgreSQL. AWS Terraform, flowable.

Technical Consultor Lead - 01/2020 - 12/2020 Novacomp. San José.

- Work with a client of this company, in the development of security requirements for their web platform by analizying and re implementing all the front-end and backend to login using the security platform provided.
- Implemented from scratch all the mobile application for the car tax registration (marchamo) for the client in a period of two months with no issues in production.

SKILLS

- ✓ Project management
- ✓ Strong decision maker
- ✓ Complex problem solver
- ✓ Teamwork
- Auto coaching
- Proactive and analytical
- Innovative
- Collaborative
- Fast learner.

- Artificial Intelligence
- Microservices
- Subversional Environments (SVN, Github, JIRA)
- Web accessibility knowledge (W3C)
- IT auditing knowledge
- Normative knowledge in: ITIL, SUGEF, COBIT, ISO 9000. ISO14000, ISO17799 and 27001.

PROGRAMMING KNOWLEDGE

Advanced: Python, Android SDK -Medium Frameworks Java: Spring, Hibernate, JSF, J2EE, JSP, Servlets, Hibernate, Struts, C++, HTML 5, SQL Server, Oracle, MySQL, JMeter

Intermediate: React JS. Redux. Hooks, PySpark

Technologies applied: Java, struts 2, Hibernate, Thymeleaf, Spring, Spring boot, rest and soap services.

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

Tutor - 02/2017 - present. UNED, San José.

Investigation of biometric software for anti-plagiarism in exams using IA face detection and IoT. Programming courses, Databases, Operations Research. Artificial Intelligence for information systems

Technologies applied: Python, OpenCV, Raspberry Pi and Flask Framework, MySQL, Oracle, SQL Server.

Professor - 06/2013 - present. Universidad Nacional, Heredia

Professor of the computer school. I have given courses like: Programming IV (Web Programming), Programming I, Programming II, Web Programming (Bachelor), Computing and Information Technology 2 (Service Course Survey School), Computer Science and SQL Programming (ServiceCourse, Geography School). ICAI trainer (basic PHP, intermediate PHP, advanced PHP). Computer Systems course for administrators, Data Structures and Artificial Intelligence.

Technologies applied: Java, Jasper Reports, Visual Basic, C++, C# (.NET) y PHP con frameworks (Laravel y CakePHP), ATOM, bootstrap, jquery, NodeJS, Angular, JSON, JAX-RS, JAX-WS, Python, TensorFlow, Pytorch, OpenCV

EDUCATION

- 05/2021 06/2022 Three points. Barcelona University. Artificial Inteligence Master Degree
- 02/2018 10/2020 Universidad Estatal a Distancia de Costa Rica.
 Teaching degree with an emphasis in Computer Science
- 01/2014 12/2014 Universidad para la cooperación internacional Project Manager Administration Master Degree (PMA).
- 02/2005 06/2012. Universidad Nacional, UNA Facultad de Ciencias Sociales, Escuela de administración Bachelor of Business Administration Degree
- 02/2007 11/2012. Universidad Nacional, UNA. Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Escuela de Informática Information Systems Engineering degree.
- 01/2009 12/2009 Universidad de Costa Rica. Escuela de Administración de Negocios, Continuing Education Programs. Graduated in Information Technology audit technical course (ITAT).
- 02/2003 11/2007. Universidad Nacional, UNA. Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Escuela de Informática Graduate in Computer Systems Engineering

LANGUAGES

- Spanish 100% native
- English 95%

CERTIFICATIONS

- AWS Certified Solutions Architect (2024)
- AWS Certified Developer (2023)
- SDKUNA Framework (2016). Given by IT Department in Universidad Nacional. As part of this training, now I am professor of the course too.
- Training in HTML5 (2013). Given by CENFOTEC in LAFISE Bank.
- Accessibility WCAG 2.0 (2016). Practical application course and web accessibility design. Given by SIDAR. Madrid, Spain.
- Advanced Java. Given by ICAI, UNA
- Coursera courses: Machine Learning (2012), Neural Networks for Machine Learning (2012), An Introduction to Interactive Programming in Python (2012)